[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's a question on dealing with sensuality and lust in particular.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh... it says, eh... when, eh... when mind affected with lust is active, I try my best not to give in, eh... by having cold showers, exercising, breath counting meditation and other activities such as avoidance of perceptions that inflame the lust further.
[SPEAKER_00]: When enough time passes, the active lust is gone, but the lust is still present in that dormant sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: I've not cured the lust, but I've dealt with some of its symptoms.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, what is the cause of lust?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, what is lust a symptom of?
[SPEAKER_00]: The cause of lust is being activated from its dormant state, seems to me,
[SPEAKER_00]: Seems to be me carelessly attending to lust-inflamed perceptions, but then, even if I'm careful, still lust is there, waiting in the background, pressuring me to activate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Such awareness and restraint are quite exhausting, and the only way I know how to relax is by doing the very thing I'm not trying to do, which is to activate lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what should I do?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, sense restraint, not acting out of lust,
[SPEAKER_00]: Not aggravating the situation further, as I say often, that's the first step.
[SPEAKER_00]: All the other things that are done here, that are described here, are kind of on the level of management of lust, which obviously, that is obvious to this person.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the real problem of lust is that fact that it's
[SPEAKER_00]: That dormant state, how it refers to.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's kind of the possibility of lust is always present.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's not enough to just not have lust present in your mind throughout the day and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: You also need to keep reviewing your mind and questioning it in a sense that you want to see whether non-arisen sensual lust can arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, if you're unsure about the answer, means it can.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, doubt means, yes, it can arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: As this person asks, so, what should I do?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how can I then, having dealt with particular manifestations of lust, endure them, not having distracted myself from it, and so on, as long as I didn't act out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now, when the mind is free from those particular manifestations of lust,
[SPEAKER_00]: How do I then deal with that dormant possibility of lust manifesting and pressuring me?
[SPEAKER_00]: And the answer is, when the mind is free from the particular, you know, engagements or preoccupations with lust,
[SPEAKER_00]: And if it's not free, you have to basically endure it through the sense restraint until it calms down.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it has... it will have to calm down.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when it calms down temporarily, then you need to make the effort to contemplate the danger in those things that you're currently free from.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those... those particular, eh... infatuations with... with... with sense pleasures and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because as long as the danger doesn't become apparent, the dormant lust will still be your framework.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, you will be within the dormant lust that is waiting to be activated.
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't be stepping outside of its domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, you won't be free.
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't be
[SPEAKER_00]: In that, like, you won't be safe, to put it that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it is a question of safety, because, as, you know, various suttas describe, the whole purpose of central pleasures, and the last day inside, and so on, through carelessly attending to them, is to trap you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a trap, it's a bait,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like a fishhook that you don't see.
[SPEAKER_00]: It then keeps you bound to pretty much everything else that burdens you and overwhelms you and makes your life unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Including, like, you know, the future possibilities and liabilities to sufferings and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the true freedom then comes from not being pressured by... even by the possibilities of lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by not having the dormant lust waiting to be activated,
[SPEAKER_00]: And, so, it's not a matter of choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't just decide to not activate the dormant lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to have beforehand been developed in sense restraint, virtue, seeing the danger in the slightest fault.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, a certain mode of behavior, of wholesome mode of behavior, has been kind of become your norm.
[SPEAKER_00]: That already implies that you have developed a degree of proper recollectedness and watchfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you're not forgetting that you're not supposed to give in to lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not lapsing, you're not ignoring it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're sustaining that context.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're sustaining the, pretty much, the reasons why you want to be free from lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't forget that actually you already got some idea that it is better to be free from particular lust and dormant lust, that it's better to be free from pressure of the sense desires than to engage with them.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, of course, when they pressure you, you forget your goals, to put it that way, and then you just, you know, go against them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, once you kind of have been developed in terms of your behavior, in terms of not acting out of lust, not giving in those coarse modes that would be against the precepts, then, and as I said, when the mind is not actively gripped by lust, you have to really make the effort and just day in, day out, contemplate the danger of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what would be those, you know, traps, those baits?
[SPEAKER_00]: What are they?
[SPEAKER_00]: What are those dangers of engaging with sense pleasures that, you know, seemingly harm no one?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like,
[SPEAKER_00]: People enjoy them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not causing anybody... anyone else pain and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just... just enjoying sense desires.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, the Buddha said there is an inherent danger, a perception of danger that hasn't been developed in regard to it, because there is an inherent bait, inherent poison, inherent trap, all these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you were to see that,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the most refined central pleasure, doesn't matter on what level or scale, will be all seen equally as peril, unwanted, painful, burning, pressuring, pretty much everything else that you want to avoid.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's the contemplation of danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, so, now you want to ask yourself, so, what do I... where do I look for that danger?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, what do I look at in my body?
[SPEAKER_00]: To look at in the sense objects?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where is that danger?
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why the contemplation of danger kind of follows after the
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why understanding the gratification, the danger and the escape in regard to sense desires, in regard to one's lust, will free you from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't have to necessarily just chronologically follow this order, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes the danger will be clear, sometimes the gratification will be clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, whichever way you put forward, you will be kind of understanding everything else that's included in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you're correctly understanding the danger of sensuality, you are then understanding
[SPEAKER_00]: gratification along the right lines.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're correctly understanding where gratification is, you are understanding the danger along the right lines.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's really where the work is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not in about, like, constantly calming these and desires and calming them.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just, as I said, management.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's when you have space to think about them, when you when you're not just completely pressured, constantly pressured,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you can actually make that effort, that's where the practice is, to contemplate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you understand what gratification of sense desires is?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, say you have a desire to, I don't know, eat something agreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're not hungry, but there is something that's pressuring you to taste it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's put it that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: What would gratification be in that instance?
[SPEAKER_00]: What would the principle of gratification be behind that instance?
[SPEAKER_00]: So that then you can understand it in every instance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you want to taste something, what part of that experience is the gratification?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is the gratification when you're actually putting the food in your mouth?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is the gratification once you feel the taste and you're chewing it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or has the gratification begun even in your perception of that which is wanted and that it's pressuring you?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, on what level, you need to basically learn how to be mindful and not lose sight of, in order to recognize what the actual gratification is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the common assumption is, or gratification is, once I get the thing, then I'm gratified.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, my desires are satisfied and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not what I would have said.
[SPEAKER_00]: The gratification in sensuality has nothing to do with you getting in touch with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Touching it, tasting it, smelling it, looking at it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The gratification is on the level of delighting already at the thought of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, your mental elation, inspiration,
[SPEAKER_00]: Kind of uplifting towards the sense object.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's already your gratification.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's already where the danger is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything else is secondary.
[SPEAKER_00]: You haven't even tasted that thing you want to taste.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you just saw it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You presume that it tastes nice on the basis of its look and the smell and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now you're craving for its taste, but you are not actually tasting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, your mouth is already reacting.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're fully gripped by the desire, as if you are fully already connected with that desirable object.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, the object of your desire remains in the world untouched.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the body is getting agitated and aroused and sort of prepped for engaging with sense objects, without even engaging with sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if gratification were truly on the level of sense objects, that would not be possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would not be able
[SPEAKER_00]: to get all these reactions in the body as a result of desire, unless you have already touched and contacted the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's containing the gratification.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, since you are not tasting it, not touching it, not looking at it even, yet here you are, gripped by the desire and already feeling elated on account of it, and now you just want to go for it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you realize that what is commonly assumed as gratification, it's really the result of already... of mind already gripped by the gratification.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why gratification is insatiable, because if you take it at face value,
[SPEAKER_00]: The delight in the prospect of sensual pleasures, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your gratification has begun.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it has no end.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the framework of your mind that wants gratification, the delight... sorry, your mind that wants sensual pleasure, the delight in it, that's the framework of gratification, and you agree by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can't fill that in.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't matter how much you're engaging with things, the framework remains unchanged, and it's forcing and pressuring you to engage.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: For as long as you look for the danger of sensuality on the level of the actual objects, you won't find it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to look at the level of your delight and your inspiration towards sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like... and, again, you would start seeing that if you then make the effort and practice sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you would see how much the mind jumps even just at the mere prospect, at the mere thought, an image of sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, fundamentally,
[SPEAKER_00]: The value of experiencing sense pleasures is not seen as harmful, it's not seen as a debt, as a doubt, as a pain, all the things that the Buddha listed.
[SPEAKER_00]: For as long as you don't see that value of your mental relation towards sense pleasures, if you don't see that as the root of the danger, you will be the victim of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, you will be basically acting out of it and putting the sense objects that are truly just second, as first, as the root of the problem, while the actual root of the problem remains invisible.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, same, because, see, you think the problem is on the level of sense objects, then you try to counter and look at the
[SPEAKER_00]: The sense objects you don't want, the beautiful, the ugly, hoping that will cancel the beautiful, but then you just end up being equally attracted, elated, wanting to further gratify the ugly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because any sense object basically just starts serving the purpose of the framework of gratification that you are still very much holding on to and fueling through your careless attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: Careless attention means putting the first... putting second is first and first and second.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what ayoniso.
[SPEAKER_00]: yoniso, manasikāra, the wise attention, the proper attention, means seeing things in the right order, seeing first as first and second as second.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's a necessary prerequisite for the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: ayoniso means basically attending wrongly, attending that which is second as the first, as the reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: Parabuddha on numerous occasions said that sense objects, beautiful sense objects, are not desire, are not sensuality in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's man's desire and lust, his thoughts of desire and lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why there is sensuality in regard to beautiful things in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: He, the Tathāgata, has freed himself from such thoughts, such elations, such delights,
[SPEAKER_00]: He freed himself from gratification through understanding the danger of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, for him, beautiful things just remain standing in the world, but there is no desire therein.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the contemplation.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to understand what gratification is.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to start discerning that mental delight, which is the background, pretty much, of your experience when you're gripped by the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: by the prospect of the pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, that delight is not there as the object of what you're doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's your state of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, you might be attracted by sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, but you actually recognize peripherally, oh, is there an elation in my mind and the thought of a pleasing sight?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I must not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Welcome, further delight, accept, act out of.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sight, sounds, smell, taste, touches then become truly seen in the right place as secondary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, first, you need to restrain in regard to those, as I keep repeating, because unless you restrain in regard to sight, sounds, smell, taste, touches, you're not gonna see what's peripheral to them, because you don't even see them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't see them, because at the slightest touch of the pressure, you act towards them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, but, you know, we're presupposing that that's... that has been developed and sustained and protected.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, actually, you can get to recognize that it's that mental elation, that zeal.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, in Pali, the word for desire, chanda, is often used for zeal, just in general.
[SPEAKER_00]: Good zeal, in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have this... any like a zeal towards sense objects, that you can gain the pleasure from, yeah, that's basically what that lust, what that desire is, and that delight that the Buddha talks about, and that's something you have to become familiar and discern even before it takes over you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it... on that level, you will be able to then see the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the danger, as I would say, will become apparent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the danger are not the objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, no matter how much you try... how hard you're trying to see the danger in the objects, it's always kind of secondary.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always going to last for a while, but then it expires.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't really fit with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't really apply, because that's not what it's supposed to apply.
[SPEAKER_00]: The danger is on the level of the gratification.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, once you start understanding what the actual gratification of sensuality is, you then get to see, ah, that's the danger, that's the bait, that's the trap, that's the matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I just keep an eye,
[SPEAKER_00]: On that level, and not allow my mind to jump at the prospect of elation, at the prospect of that central zeal and delight, I'm safe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing else that used to follow can befall me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the clearer that becomes, then the clearer the danger of accepting it becomes as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you fully understood the escape too.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, the escape, it means protecting that mind, so to not jump at the prospect of zeal, delight, acceptance, inspiration towards central pleasures.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you protect it,
[SPEAKER_00]: You will be free eventually.
[SPEAKER_00]: How long it will take depends how much you were dependent on those sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_00]: But eventually, you will be free from that pressure, because that pressure, actually, pressure of sensuality, or sensuality in itself, requires fueling, requires you accepting, requires that zeal, renewing each time, sort of, when you choose to give in and kind of, you know, let it run its course until you can get, until you can squeeze all the pleasure out that you can from from things that that incite you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But see, that's the fuel that then
[SPEAKER_00]: Perpetuates.
[SPEAKER_00]: Perpetuates the pressure, makes it stronger, makes it sort of harder to see, because it increases the burden of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know, your perspective is basically shrinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: The more you give in to sensuality, the harder it will be to give it up later on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same like with any other addiction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, understanding the gratification,
[SPEAKER_00]: That is on the level of delight in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you engage with it or not, that's secondary.
[SPEAKER_00]: The delight means you're already trapped.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, seeing that exactly, delight means I'm already trapped, means, oh, that's the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you understand the gratification, you are understanding the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, by being mindful of the danger, you will not set your foot in the trap.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you escape the trap.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, understanding danger, understanding gratification, danger in the escape in regard to sensuality, will completely remove any basis for further fueling of your sense... of your dependence on sensual pleasures, and then you will be free from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then there will be no more dormant things lying around there, because, again, you cease to fuel them and they would have faded away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those those dormant possibilities of engaging with lust, it doesn't matter how subtle, how dormant they are fundamentally, they... you only... you can only engage with them through
[SPEAKER_00]: Mental zeal, acceptance, inspiration, delight, welcoming of such thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's your gratification.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you lose mindfulness in regard to it, that's how these dormant things become activated.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, hence, again, go back to the sensory strain, seeing the danger in the slightest fold, watchfulness, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: recollectedness, recognizing, like, oh, okay, I'm free from lust now, but
[SPEAKER_00]: Can lust arise in me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Later on, today or tomorrow, can things become activated, as the original question says, and would I know, like, how to deactivate it?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and again, that's another thing that we would say.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I know how to prevent non-arisen lust from arising, or how to make the arisen lust disappear?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, the Arisen Lust doesn't need to run its course before it disappears.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Arisen Lust is activated because you plugged it in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's say like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's active because it's plugged in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Plugged into what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Into your framework of delight and gratification.
[SPEAKER_00]: of your zeal, of your value of the pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what gives it life, keeps it active, keeps it alive, keeps it pressuring you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, at any given time, theoretically at least, you can see that that's the root of the problem and that that's the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by seeing that, you have unplugged it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, whatever pressuring sense objects that were pressuring you with lust, will be just seen as just objects, matter, form, perceptions, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: The work, then, is on the level of not just sort of constantly, like, calming your mind, calming your mind, calming your mind, calming your mind, because that pretty much requires the disturbance in order to calm it, and disturbs, and gets this calm.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's only calming your mind, it's just managing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not uprooting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The work is, when you are sufficiently calm, when I say that, and by that I mean when you have enough space to stop and think about it, when you're not just bombarded by sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, then the actual work is thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Making the effort to not just discern this gratification and inspiration and zeal and delight once or twice.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hundreds of times.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Keep discerning.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if it's clear, then sustain that clarity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Keep that context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, so now it's clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is my gratification.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if it's clear, means you're mindful of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means now, you don't need to think about it directly, because now you're clear that it's your elation.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where the gratification is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is no elation now.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no elation now.
[SPEAKER_00]: You go about your day.
[SPEAKER_00]: Elation pops up.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will immediately see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will immediately see the manifestation of a trap.
[SPEAKER_00]: The danger will be immediately recognized and that's enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I must know you don't need to get rid of the trap.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, in order to get rid of the trap, you'll be reaching for a trap and get trapped.
[SPEAKER_00]: The whole point is, as they would often say in numerous suttas, is to learn how to basically go around the trap.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not engage with things that will trap you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not eat the food that contains the bait.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't mean you mustn't look at smell or taste or touch anything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's that gratification and delight and zeal and inspiration, that's the bait.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that pretty much then determines whether you should engage with things or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, something externally might not necessarily be against the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, for example, yeah, so eating something that you want to taste is not against the precepts, if it's within the right time.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you're fully, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: oriented with that gratification and zeal towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why you shouldn't do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because an object in itself is good or bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because now it is rooted in clear furthering of my already gripping gripped mind by gratification and and that delight and zeal and welcoming and I want it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you are now fully activated
[SPEAKER_00]: In that state of lust, and that's why it's a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why you shouldn't do it, and instead contemplate the danger, not in the cake or whatever you want to eat, but the danger in the state of a mind affected with that desirous zeal.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the trap.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the framework.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, I'm repeating the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, on another occasion, you might not have that present at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just... it's still factually agreeable taste.
[SPEAKER_00]: You still factually want to eat it, but there is no zeal.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how do you know that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you know that if you don't eat it, your mental composure will not change.
[SPEAKER_00]: If something would happen to it, if you were to give it away, if somebody else did it, nothing would change internally.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is no zeal, there is no inspiration, there is no... there is no chanda towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you can eat it, because you're not acting out of desire.